<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
 http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.   
-->
<chapter id="ref_guide_slice">
  <title>
    Distributed Persistence
  </title>
  <para>
  The standard JPA runtime environment works with a <emphasis>single</emphasis>
  database instance. OpenJPA can be extended via plug-in to work with 
  multiple databases within the same transaction without any change to the 
  existing application. This capability of OpenJPA for distributed 
  database environment is called <emphasis>Slice</emphasis> and is explained in 
  the following sections.
  </para>
  
  <section id="slice_overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
    Enterprise applications are increasingly deployed for distributed database
    environments. The reasons for distributed, often horizontally-partitioned 
    database environment can be to counter massive data growth, to 
    support multiple external clients on a hosted platform or many other 
    practical scenarios that can benefit from data partitioning.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Any JPA-based user application has to address serious technical and conceptual
    challenges to directly interact with a set of physical databases
    within a single transaction. 
    Slice encapsulates the complexity of distributed database environment 
    via the abstraction of <emphasis>virtual</emphasis> database which internally 
    manages multiple physical databases. We refer each physical database instance 
    as <emphasis>slice</emphasis>. 
    <emphasis>Virtualization</emphasis> of distributed databases 
    makes OpenJPA object management kernel and 
    the user application to work in the same way as in the case of a single physical 
    database.
    </para>
  </section>
  
    <section id="features_and_limitations">
       <title>Salient Features</title>
         <section><title>Transparency</title>
            <para>
              The existing application or the persistent domain model requires 
              <emphasis>no change</emphasis> to upgrade from a single database 
              to a distributed database environment. 
            </para>
         </section>
         
         <section><title>Custom Distribution Policy</title>
            <para>
             User application decides how the newly persistent instances be 
             distributed across the database slices. The data
             distribution policy across the slices may be based on the attribute 
             of the data itself. For example, all Customer whose first name begins with
             character 'A' to 'M' will be stored in one slice while names
             beginning with 'N' to 'Z' will be stored in another slice. 
             </para>
             <para>
             This custom data distribution policy is specified by implementing  
             <classname>org.apache.openjpa.slice.DistributionPolicy</classname>
             interface by the user application.
             </para>
          
             <para> 
             Slice tracks the original database for existing instances. When
             an application issues a query, the resultant instances can be loaded 
             from different slices. This tracking is important as subsequent
             update to any of these instances is committed to the appropriate 
             original database slice. 
            </para>
            
            <note>
            <para>
            You can find the original slice of an instance <code>pc</code> by 
            the static utility method  
            <methodname>SlicePersistence.getSlice(pc)</methodname>.
            This method returns the slice identifier string associated with the
            given <emphasis>managed</emphasis> instance. If the instance is not
            being managed then the method return null because any unmanaged or
            detached instance is not associated with any slice. 
            </para>
            </note>
            
            <para>
            <warning>Currently, there is no provision for migrating an 
            existing instance from one slice to another.
            </warning>
            </para>
         </section>
         
         <section><title>Heterogeneous Database</title>
            <para> 
              Each slice can be configured independently with its own JDBC 
              driver and other connection parameters. Hence the target database 
              environment can constitute of heterogeneous databases. 
            </para>
        </section>
        
        <section><title>Parallel Execution</title>
            <para> 
              All database operations such as query, commit or flush operates
              in parallel across the database slices. The execution threading
              policy is configurable. 
            </para>
         </section>
         
         <section><title>Distributed Query</title>
            <para>
            The queries are executed across all slices and the results are
            merged into a single list. The query result that includes 
            <code>ORDER BY</code> clause are sorted correctly by merging 
            results from each individual slice. 
            </para>
            The queries that specify an aggregate projection such as 
            <code>COUNT()</code>, <code>MAX()</code>, <code>MIN()</code> 
            and <code>SUM()</code>
            are correctly evaluated <emphasis>only if</emphasis> they 
            return a single result.
            <para>
            </para>
            <para>
            <warning>
            The aggregate operation <code>AVG()</code> is not supported.
            </warning>
            </para>
            
         </section>
         
         <section><title>Targeted Query</title>
            <para>
            You can target the query only to a subset of slices rather than
            all slices by setting a <emphasis>hint</emphasis>. The hint key
            <code>openjpa.hint.slice.Target</code> is set on any query and 
            hint value is
            comma-separated list of slice identifiers. The following 
            example shows how to target a query only to slice <code>"One"</code>
                          
            <programlisting>
              <![CDATA[EntityManager em = ...;
              em.getTransaction().begin();
              String hint = "openjpa.hint.slice.Target";
              Query query = em.createQuery("SELECT p FROM PObject").setHint(hint, "One");
              List result = query.getResultList();
              // verify that each instance is originaing from the given slice
              for (Object pc : result) {
                 String sliceOrigin = SlicePersistence.getSlice(pc);
                 assertTrue ("One", sliceOrigin);
              }
              ]]>
            </programlisting> 
            </para>
         </section>
         
         
         <section><title>Distributed Transaction</title>
            <para> 
            The database slices participate in a global transaction provided
            each slice is configured with a XA-compliant JDBC driver, even
            when the persistence unit is configured for <code>RESOURCE_LOCAL</code>
            transaction.
            </para>
            <para>
            <warning>
            If any of the configured slices is not XA-compliant <emphasis>and</emphasis> 
            the persistence unit is configured for <code>RESOURCE_LOCAL</code>
            transaction then each slice is committed without any two-phase
            commit protocol. If commit on any slice fails, then atomic nature of
            the transaction is not ensured.
            </warning>
            </para>
          </section>
   
    
    
        
         <section id="collocation_constraint"><title>Collocation Constraint</title>
            <para> 
            No relationship can exist across database slices. In O-R mapping parlance,
            this condition translates to the limitation that the closure of an object graph must be 
            <emphasis>collocated</emphasis> in the same database.
            For example, consider a domain model where Person relates to Adress.
            Person X refers to Address A while Person Y refers to Address B. 
            Collocation Constraint means that <emphasis>both</emphasis> X and A 
            must be stored in the same
            database slice. Similarly Y and B must be stored in a single slice.
            </para>
            <para>
            Slice, however, helps to maintain collocation constraint automatically.
            The instances in the closure set of any newly persistent instance 
            reachable via cascaded relationship is stored in the same slice.
            The user-defined distribution policy requires to supply the slice 
            for the root instance only.
            </para>
         </section>
    </section>
  
  <section id="slice_configuration">
    <title>Usage</title>
    <para>
     Slice is activated via the following property settings:
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>How to activate Slice Runtime?</title>
      <para>
       The basic configuration property is 
       <programlisting> 
        <![CDATA[ <property name="openjpa.BrokerFactory" value="slice"/>]]>
       </programlisting> 
       This critical configuration activates a specialized factory class aliased
       as <code>slice</code> to create object management kernel that
       can work against multiple databases.  
      </para>
    </section> 
    
    <section>
      <title>How to configure each database slice?</title>
      <para>
      Each database slice is identified by a logical name unique within a
      persistent unit. The list of the slices is specified by 
      <code>openjpa.slice.Names</code> property.
      For example, specify three slices named <code>"One"</code>, 
      <code>"Two"</code> and <code>"Three"</code> as follows:
      <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[ <property name="openjpa.slice.Names" value="One, Two, Three"/>]]>
      </programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
      This property is not mandatory. If this property is not specified then
      the configuration is scanned for logical slice names. Any property
      <code>"abc"</code> of the form <code>openjpa.slice.XYZ.abc</code> will 
      register a slice with logical
      name <code>"XYZ"</code>.
      </para>
      <para>
      The order of the names is significant when no <code>openjpa.slice.Master</code> 
      property is not specified. Then the persistence unit is scanned to find
      all configured slice names and they are ordered alphabetically.  
      </para>
      
      <para>
       Each database slice properties can be configured independently. 
       For example, the
       following configuration will register two slices with logical name 
       <code>One</code> and <code>Two</code>.
       <programlisting> 
        <![CDATA[<property name="openjpa.slice.One.ConnectionURL" value="jdbc:mysql:localhost//slice1"/>
        <property name="openjpa.slice.Two.ConnectionURL" value="jdbc:mysql:localhost//slice2"/>]]>
       </programlisting> 
      </para>
      
      <para>
       Any OpenJPA specific property can be configured per slice basis. 
       For example, the following configuration will use two different JDBC 
       drivers for slice <code>One</code> and <code>Two</code>.
       <programlisting> 
        <![CDATA[<property name="openjpa.slice.One.ConnectionDriverName" value="com.mysql.jdbc.Driver"/>
        <property name="openjpa.slice.Two.ConnectionDriverName" value="com.mysql.jdbc.jdbc2.optional.MysqlXADataSource"/>]]>
       </programlisting> 
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Any property if unspecified for a particular slice will be defaulted by
        corresponding OpenJPA property. For example, consider following three slices
        <programlisting> 
         <![CDATA[<property name="openjpa.slice.One.ConnectionURL"          value="jdbc:mysql:localhost//slice1"/>
         <property name="openjpa.slice.Two.ConnectionURL"          value="jdbc:mysql:localhost//slice2"/>
         <property name="openjpa.slice.Three.ConnectionURL"        value="jdbc:oracle:localhost//slice3"/>

         <property name="openjpa.ConnectionDriverName"     value="com.mysql.jdbc.Driver"/>
         <property name="openjpa.slice.Three.ConnectionDriverName" value="oracle.jdbc.Driver"/>]]>
        </programlisting> 
        In this example, <code>Three</code> will use slice-specific
        <code>oracle.jdbc.Driver</code> driver while slice
        <code>One</code> and <code>Two</code> will use
        the driver <code>com.mysql.jdbc.Driver</code> as 
        specified by <code>openjpa.ConnectionDriverName</code> 
        property value.
      </para>
    </section>
     
    <section id="distribution_policy">
       <title>Implement DistributionPolicy interface</title>
       <para>
        Slice needs to determine which slice will persist a new instance. 
        The application can only decide this policy (for example, 
        all PurchaseOrders before April 30 goes to slice <code>One</code>,
        all the rest goes to slice <code>Two</code>). This is why
        the application has to implement 
        <code>org.apache.openjpa.slice.DistributionPolicy</code> and
        specify the implementation class in configuration
        <programlisting> 
         <![CDATA[ <property name="openjpa.slice.DistributionPolicy" value="com.acme.foo.MyOptimialDistributionPolicy"/>]]>
        </programlisting>
       </para>
       
       <para>
        The interface <code>org.apache.openjpa.slice.DistributionPolicy</code>
        is simple with a single method. The complete listing of the
        documented interface follows:
       <programlisting> 
       <![CDATA[ 
public interface DistributionPolicy {
    /**
     * Gets the name of the slice where a given instance will be stored.
     *  
     * @param pc The newly persistent or to-be-merged object. 
     * @param slices name of the configured slices.
     * @param context persistence context managing the given instance.
     * 
     * @return identifier of the slice. This name must match one of the
     * configured slice names. 
     * @see DistributedConfiguration#getSliceNames()
     */
    String distribute(Object pc, List<String> slices, Object context);
}
]]>
       </programlisting>
        </para>
        
        <para>
        While implementing a distribution policy the most important thing to
        remember is <link linkend="collocation_constraint">collocation constraint</link>.
        Because Slice can not establish or query any cross-database relationship, all the
        related instances must be stored in the same database slice. 
 
        Slice can determine the closure of a root object by traversal of 
        cascaded relationships. Hence user-defined policy has to only decide the
        database for the root instance that is the explicit argument to 
        <methodname>EntityManager.persist()</methodname> call.
        Slice will ensure that all other related instances that gets persisted by cascade
        is assigned to the same database slice as that of the root instance.
        However, the user-defined distribution policy must return the
        same slice identifier for the instances that are logically related but
        not cascaded for persist. 
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <title>Configuration Properties</title>
    <para>
    The properties to configure Slice can be classified in two broad groups.
The <emphasis>global</emphasis> properties apply to all the slices, for example,
the thread pool used to execute the queries in parallel or the transaction 
manager used to coordinate transaction across multiple slices. 
The <emphasis>per-slice</emphasis> properties apply to individual slice, for example,
the JDBC connection URL of a slice.
   </para>
   
   <section>
     <title>Global Properties</title>
     
     <section>
        <title>openjpa.slice.DistributionPolicy</title>
        <para>
         This <emphasis>mandatory</emphasis> plug-in property determines how newly
         persistent instances are distributed across individual slices. 
         The value of this property is a fully-qualified class name that implements
         <ulink url="../javadoc/org/apache/openjpa/slice/DistributionPolicy.html">
         <classname>org.apache.openjpa.slice.DistributionPolicy</classname>
         </ulink> interface.
        </para>
     </section>
     
     <section><title>openjpa.slice.Lenient</title>
      <para>
        This boolean plug-in property controls the behavior when one or more slice 
        can not be connected or unavailable for some other reasons.
        If <code>true</code>, the unreachable slices are ignored. If 
        <code>false</code> then any unreachable slice will raise an exception
        during startup.
        </para>
        <para>
        By default this value is set to <code>false</code> i.e. all configured
        slices must be available.
        </para> 
     </section>

     <section>
      <title>openjpa.slice.Master</title>
      <para>
       This plug-in property can be used to identify the name of the master slice. 
       Master slice is used when a primary key is to be generated from a database sequence. 
       </para>
       <para>
        By default the master slice is the first slice in the list of configured slice names. 
       </para>
       <para>
              <warning>
              Currently, there is no provision to use sequence from 
              multiple database slices.
              </warning>
       </para>
     </section>
    
     <section>
        <title>openjpa.slice.Names</title>
        <para>
         This plug-in property can be used to register the logical slice names.
         The value of this property is comma-separated list of slice names. 
         The ordering of the names in this list is 
         <emphasis>significant</emphasis> because 
         <link linkend="distribution_policy">DistributionPolicy</link> receives 
         the input argument of the slice names in the same order.
        </para>
        <para>
        If logical slice names are not registered explicitly via this property,
        then all logical slice names available in the persistence unit are 
        registered. The ordering of the slice names in this case is alphabetical.  
        </para>
        <para>
        If logical slice names are registered explicitly via this property, then
        any logical slice that is available in the persistence unit but excluded
        from this list is ignored. 
        </para>
     </section>
    
     <section>
        <title>openjpa.slice.ThreadingPolicy</title>
        <para>
        This plug-in property determines the nature of thread pool being used 
        for database operations such as query or flush on individual slices. 
        The value of the property is a 
        fully-qualified class name that implements 
        <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/ExecutorService.html">
        <classname>java.util.concurrent.ExecutorService</classname>
        </ulink> interface.  
        Two pre-defined pools can be chosen via their aliases namely 
        <code>fixed</code> or <code>cached</code>.
        </para>
        <para>
        The pre-defined alias <code>cached</code> activates a 
        <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/Executors.html#newCachedThreadPool()">cached thread pool</ulink>. 
        A cached thread pool creates new threads as needed, but will reuse 
        previously constructed threads when they are available. This pool 
        is suitable in scenarios that execute many short-lived asynchronous tasks.
        The way Slice uses the thread pool to execute database operations is 
        akin to such scenario and hence <code>cached</code> is the default 
        value for this plug-in property.  
        </para>
        <para>
        The <code>fixed</code> alias activates a 
        <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/Executors.html#newFixedThreadPool(int)">fixed thread pool</ulink>.
        The fixed thread pool can be further parameterized with 
        <code>CorePoolSize</code>, <code>MaximumPoolSize</code>, 
        <code>KeepAliveTime</code> and <code>RejectedExecutionHandler</code>. 
        The meaning of these parameters are described in 
        <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/ThreadPoolExecutor.html">JavaDoc</ulink>.
        The users can exercise finer control on thread pool behavior via these
        parameters.
        By default, the core pool size is <code>10</code>, maximum pool size is
        also <code>10</code>, keep alive time is <code>60</code> seconds and 
        rejected execution is 
        <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/ThreadPoolExecutor.AbortPolicy.html">aborted</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
        Both of the pre-defined aliases can be parameterized with a fully-qualified
        class name that implements 
        <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/ThreadFactory.html">
        <classname>java.util.concurrent.ThreadFactory</classname>
        </ulink> interface.
        </para>
     </section>
      
     <section>
      <title>openjpa.slice.TransactionPolicy</title>
      <para>
      This plug-in property determines the policy for transaction commit 
      across multiple slices. The value of this property is a fully-qualified 
      class name that implements 
      <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/sdk_1.3/techdocs/api/javax/transaction/TransactionManager.html">
      <classname>javax.transaction.TransactionManager</classname> 
      </ulink> interface. 
      </para>
      <para>
      Three pre-defined policies can be chosen
      by their aliases namely <code>default</code>,
      <code>xa</code> and <code>jndi</code>. 
      </para>
      <para>
      The <code>default</code> policy employs 
      a Transaction Manager that commits or rolls back transaction on individual
      slices <emphasis>without</emphasis> a two-phase commit protocol. 
      It does <emphasis>not</emphasis>
      guarantee atomic nature of transaction across all the slices because if
      one or more slice fails to commit, there is no way to rollback the transaction
      on other slices that committed successfully.
      </para>
      <para>
      The <code>xa</code> policy employs a Transaction Manager that that commits 
      or rolls back transaction on individual
      slices using a two-phase commit protocol. The prerequisite to use this scheme
      is, of course, that all the slices must be configured to use
      XA-compliant JDBC driver. 
      </para>
      <para>
      The <code>jndi</code> policy employs a Transaction Manager by looking up the
      JNDI context. The prerequisite to use this transaction
      manager is, of course, that all the slices must be configured to use
      XA-compliant JDBC driver. 
      <warning>This JNDI based policy is not available currently.</warning>
      </para>
    </section>
   </section>
   
   <section>
     <title>Per-Slice Properties</title>
     <para>
     Any OpenJPA property can be configured for each individual slice. The property name
     is of the form <code>openjpa.slice.[Logical slice name].[OpenJPA Property Name]</code>.
     For example, <code>openjpa.slice.One.ConnectionURL</code> where <code>One</code>
     is the logical slice name and <code>ConnectionURL</code> is an OpenJPA property
     name. 
     </para>
     <para>
     If a property is not configured for a specific slice, then the value for
     the property equals to the corresponding <code>openjpa.*</code> property.
     </para>
   </section>
  
</chapter>
  
